All righty. Good morning everyone. I
hope you've had a wonderful week. Uh I
call this meeting of the medical
psilocybin advisory board to order.
Welcome everyone. Thank you for being
here and your comm continued service to
the board. In order to establish a
quorum, we'll do a quick roll call. I
the chair Ian Dunham here. Dan Jennings
>> here. Uh Chris Pescusi.
>> Uh Brenda Burgard
>> here,
>> Desba.
>> Larry Leman
>> here,
>> and Alana Dances.
So the only two I have marked absent are
Desba and Alana Dances. So that
establishes a quorum for us. I will go
ahead and turn over to our uh do staff
for opening statement.
>> Okay, good morning everybody. Uh I just
wanted to thank everybody again for
being here today. My name is Dominic
Zerlo uh and I am the center director
for medical cannabis and psilocybin. Um,
and so just as a part of our usual uh,
welcoming, I just want to make sure that
everybody does know that if you have
questions about the program, you can
send email to medical.silicybin
dooh.nm.gov.
And also listed are our program website
uh, as well as the advisory board
website. Those both uh, because I know
looking at them just on a screen
sometimes is difficult to get to. If you
Google medical psilocybin
NMD do you'll be taken pretty much your
first uh re the first response through a
search will bring you to those pages. Um
we do and we will continue to be posting
the meeting invitation on the medical
psilocybin web page and that will
continue u for as long as the program is
continuing. Um, in addition to that,
what I just wanted to go ahead and do
right now, um, if I, uh, may, and,
pardon me, I'm trying to get to that
next slide, is just show the agenda, and
I will turn it back on over uh, to um,
Ian as far as for starting uh, the
meeting itself. We do have several
program staff that are here. Um, and
those include Brenda Martinez, who is
our deputy director, Johnny Musher, who
is our management analyst. Uh, Selena
uh, Mononttoya, who is our, um,
financial director. Um, we have Kathy
Ojiri who is our project manager for it.
Uh, we have Carmen Batista who is one of
our health educators and who will also
be assisting during this process. And uh
we have Rosalie Nava who is our health
education program manager. Uh we may
have some other staff members who join.
We do apologize on behalf of Jorge
Gonzalez who is our um program manager
for the medical psilocybin program. He
had delayed attending his new employee
orientation to be able to attend the
meeting last week, but today he had to
do it today or missed that training. and
so he is attending that today, but we
will be sure to update him on
information um as needed. Um so with
that, I'll turn it back to you Ian and
the agenda is up on the screen.
>> All right. So the agenda for today is
just to adopt our bylaws, set our
priorities, our committee formation, um
as well as hearing an update from the
program. Uh the chair would entertain a
motion to adopt the agenda as proposed.
I motion to adopt the agenda. And this
is Dan. I'll second that.
Perfect. With the agenda,
um if there are no objections, the
agenda is adopted.
Um and we can move on to our update from
the program.
>> Thank you, Ian. Um, so just as an update
from the program is since it's been a
week since the last meeting, there has
while there's been a lot of movement
with regard to getting items set up for
the board. Uh, and we're again working
towards getting some of the items
established and we'll be working with
the board as far as priorities, which is
actually one of the agenda items today.
I did want to let everybody know that if
people are interested in getting updates
for the program, uh, and this will
include the advisory board, we do have
an eupdate system. And basically the way
to do that is if you navigate to the
nmhealth.org
page, you would then see in the upper
right hand side, it says sign up for
e-news.
And uh at that point if you click on
that it will take you to a registration
form where you can put in your
information and then you can select the
different areas of interest that you may
have. So for example we do have here
both medical psilocybin and medical
cannabis. There's also infectious
disease, family health and several other
topics. Just select the areas that
you're interested in and then click sign
up. The system may actually ask you to
confirm you are not a robot. Um, please
of course if you are not a robot,
confirm that you are not one. And then
you will be signed up for our e-news.
And through that we're providing updates
about everything from uh new positions
in the program to uh updates uh the
advisory board meetings and just other
information in general. Um, so if
anybody at any point would like to sign
up for those, you're welcome to do so.
We did have a couple of questions that
were offered during the public comment
and I just like to address them. Uh, if
there are patients who are interested in
the services, while we do not have them
yet at this time, uh, because we have to
get everything implemented, um, and that
is a part of the process here with the
advisory board. um we will still try to
do our best to help guide you into other
services if you have not had them. So
those individuals are welcome to reach
out through the medical.silocybin
at dooh.nm.gov
email and we'll do our best to help with
regard to that.
The other thing I wanted to bring up is
there was the question about why for why
there was the uh the speed up of the
timeline and just to address that for
everybody who's here on the meeting is
what's really been happening is we've
been getting a very large amount of
inquiries as to when will the program
start? Please have the program start.
And we even heard in the public comment
last week that there are people who
really need this and believe that this
is going to be extraordinarily
beneficial and life-changing for them.
And so with that in mind and with
discussions with the secretary and that
the secretary has had with the
governor's office, it was determined
that we would speed up the timeline to
get the initial implementation. Now,
this does not mean it's going to be a
full program with every aspect
determined, but it means that we will be
able to at least by next December of 26,
we will be able to serve some patients.
And again, it may not have all of the
options, but at least to have some of
the options so we can help those people
who are most in need and to do so as
quickly as we can. We still are looking
at everything to ensure and with the
help of the board especially to ensure
that things are being done in safe and
therapeutic ways and that is going to be
our highest priority as we implement the
program to ensure safety in that
therapeutic session. And so just to let
people know that is what is happening
that is what is occurring. We are of
course going to be working very closely
with the board and other advocates to
ensure all of that moves forward and
especially with regard to uh the safety
aspects of this. Um and with that uh
that is all that I have at this time.
I'll turn it back on over to you uh Ian.
>> All righty. So the next thing we had to
go over was the adoption of the bylaws
or operating procedures, whatever you
wanted to call it. Um, Dominic, do you
have the bylaws to share?
>> Yes. Give me just a moment to switch
over.
>> Well, um, the proposed bylaws have been
distributed and discussed previously. At
this time, we do need formal board
action. Is there a motion regarding the
adoption of the bylaws?
>> Um, this is Larry Leman. I I just had
one reminder um thing. Um, the original
bylaw stated that a majority could
change who's the chair or the vice
chair. I I think I I would favor it
being a majority rather than a twothirds
vote. So that that would be my only
suggestion.
>> I would
>> and that's obviously not meant to have
any implication. I think I I'm delighted
Ian as as being a chair. It just seems
like having majority be able to do
something makes sense.
>> Okay. Uh would you like to amend the
vice chair as well?
Yes, I I think I would.
>> Okay. Um I'm perfectly fine with that.
Um so if we had changes
>> Chris has his hand raised.
>> Oh, go on Chris. Sorry.
>> Um well, De's bot I think is having an
issue with her link. I don't know if
somebody can send her a new one.
>> I got it.
>> Okay, you never mind.
And then
>> also I did want to um actually before we
move to this item as a whole I saw that
Desba and a representative for the HCA
have joined. Um
so let me mark their attendance.
Okay. Um so yeah to move it with the
majority. Do we have a motion to adopt
it as revised?
Um Ian, if I'm
>> Yeah, go for it.
>> Oh, if I just may. Um I did want to
bring up one other item and this was a
request um from uh the HCA member Alana
Dances and it's due to her new position
and to to the frequency of the meetings.
HCA wants to ensure that they are going
to be able to be involved, but the
frequency that's going to be needed with
the legislative session coming up and
other duties uh that Alana Alana has,
she had asked if it would be possible
since uh the HCA is an executive board
or an executive agency if it would be
okay if she had a proxy that she would
provide in writing before the meeting if
that individual then could act on her
behalf and HCA's behalf. with regard to
voting and being here if that would be
okay. And so we did add that into the
bylaws for specifically for that HCA
position. And so I just wanted to make
sure that you all knew that that was in
there and if you have any discussion
about it u you know that you had that
option to be able to talk about it.
>> Thank you. Um, personally, given that
the legislation calls for a
representative of the HCA to be on the
board, I have no problem with um another
executive from that office
being here at the board to represent
them. Um, but I don't know how my fellow
board members feel. So, I'll open the
floor to discussion.
I think it's a uh a kind of standard
procedure especially in this kind of
thing. So um you know let me know if I'm
mistaken on that but in this kind of
situation usually there is uh like a
deferral to somebody else in some cases.
You said it would be in writing and so
it wouldn't be like a rotating person
but it would be somebody who would be
appointed.
>> That's correct Dan.
>> Okay. And then Ryan had a question.
>> Yeah. Hi, my name is Ken Ryan. I am uh
the acting chief medical officer. So I'm
assuming Alana's duties a lot of this
time as we're in a position of
transition. And just wanted to give a
little bit of background. It would still
be
um either myself, the acting CMO or our
deputy CMO. So still kind of meeting the
same clinical roles with the same
oversightes and uh mindset. So just
hopefully to add a little background as
to the plan with that.
>> Are there any other discussion?
>> All right. Um with no further
discussion, we can move to or I can
entertain a motion to adopt the bylaws.
Um with those points clarified. Oh,
Chris, go on.
>> Yeah, I'm sorry. I thought we were still
discussing the ACA board member. Um I
don't have any objection to that, but
can you go to the section um about
meeting frequency? I don't think that
allows for a lot of flexibility
and at times we may need to meet more
frequently. I feel like so if we change
um the advanced notice to 3 days that I
think that might be it a little bit
allow for a little more flexibility and
then I I don't know that we actually
need to put in there that we're going to
meet bi-weekly. Sometimes I I feel like
we might need to meet more frequently or
or less as things kind of eb and flow
throughout the process. Those are just
some thoughts I had.
>> Yeah. And I actually did redact the um
bi-weekly. I figured once we establish
the committees and um rules are kind of
propagating up from those committees, we
can meet at the call of the chair. I did
want to give at least 7 days. Um you
know, everyone here has primary jobs and
responsibilities. So I just wanted them
to have time to prepare but
realistically we can't meet until the
committees come up and say here's what
we are going to recommend under our
jurisdiction and then we have the final
say. Um so I did end up redacting that.
So I completely agree with you Chris.
And what about changing the announced
meeting announcements to three days?
That I think it might allow us to
I would recommend that we give people as
much notice as we can, but at times we
might need to move a little quicker. I
feel like
>> and Chris, just a question. You mean
that would be like the the minimum
amount of time? So typically we would be
looking at a longer period of time but
it would just be giving us that
flexibility if we had to call a larger
faster meeting. Is that what I'm
hearing?
>> Yes. Okay. Gotcha.
>> I would be amendable then to reducing
the amount of leeway to 3 days. Um as
long as that is still compliant with the
open meetings act.
Um, can I suggest something to maybe
have um
something there where we things come up?
Um, an emergency meeting and and if
those that can attend them that um those
I mean those that can't attend them uh
it won't be held against them if it if
it's an emergency meeting and it's a
short notice.
>> And I see Dominic with your hand raised.
Yes. Uh I just wanted to state that the
three days would be fine from that
standpoint uh as far as with regard to
publication and notification. So if the
board does decide to do that, we can
definitely do that aspect and just
change it. That's a simple change. Um
and then Brenda, thank you for bringing
up about the emergency meeting. We could
definitely draft language that would
just simply say um if uh you know the
board determines um that an emergency
meeting is needed um that the that we
will do our absolute best to um
essentially to put notifications out um
to the public so that they can attend.
and we could add that language and you
can still vote on the rest of the bylaws
if that's the only language and just uh
vote on that particular piece uh at the
next meeting.
Yeah, I would be amendable to um both
the three days and to add language that
if we need to call an emergency um
meeting that we are able to um that
would all work with me.
>> Uh Ryan.
>> Yeah. Uh I would just say that uh I I
hear what you guys are saying. the
shorter uh the amount of time, the
harder it's going to be for HCA to
attend. Uh just by the nature of our
work, it's it's very difficult. So, as
long as you guys are aware of that, um
it's going to be hard for us to make
those short meetings.
>> Yeah. And to piggyback off of what Dan
said, we're still going to try to do the
seven days, give everyone ample time. We
still need to establish a quorum and we
recognize that each of us have
individual responsibilities in our life.
Um, but in the event that we need to
have a little bit more wiggle room, we
lowered the threshold just so that we
don't end up um strangling ourselves
with our own bylaws. Uh, and then Chris
had a question.
>> You're muted, Chris.
I was just hoping we could go through
the bylaws one more time, section by
section, since these are going to have
longstanding implications. Um, so we can
make sure that we're all good.
>> Uh, yeah, if Dominic you would be
willing to read the bylaws, um, that
would be helpful. I can also do it. Um,
you're just the one scrolling, so I
figured it would be a little easier.
>> Absolutely. I'm more than happy to. Um,
so the first section of name and
authority is the name of this advisory
body is the medical psilocybin advisory
board, hereafter referred to as the
board. The board is established pursuant
to NMSA1 1978 section 262D8
enacted through Senate Bill 219 2025
legislative session. The statute
provides that the board is
administratively attached to the New
Mexico Department of Health. Secretary
of the Department of Health shall
appoint board members. Membership must
include individuals representing or
affiliated with the New Mexico
Healthcare Authority. an enrolled member
of an Indian tribe, nation, or PBLO
located wholly or partially in New
Mexico, a licensed behavioral health
care service provider, a mental or
behavioral health equity advocate, a
veteran of the United States Armed
Forces, and additional members as
appointed by the secretary. And I'll
pause after each section just to see if
there's any questions or concerns.
So, any questions or concerns?
Okay. Uh, duties of the board. As
provided in statute, the board shall
review and recommend to DOH medical
conditions that may benefit from the
medical use of psilocybin. Accept and
review petitions to add medical
conditions to the list of qualifying
conditions. Recommend patient
qualifications for the medical use of
psilocybin. Recommend formulation or
preparation rules and dosage standards
for psilocybin. assist uh in
establishing, monitoring, and evaluating
best practices for producers and
clinicians.
Any questions regarding that section?
Okay, I will move to the next which is
membership and voting eligibility.
A member of the board is an individual
who has been appointed by the secretary
and who meets the statutory criteria for
membership or area of expertise. A
quorum consists of a majority of
appointed members in attendance. NMSA1
1978 section 262D8A.
A member is considered present for
purposes of quorum and voting if they
are physically present at the meeting
site or participating through an
officially announced webinar or
telephonic conference.
Members who miss three consecutive
meetings may be asked to resign or may
be removed by a majority vote of the
appointed board members. A member may be
removed by the secretary within the
secretar's discretion in accordance with
the secretary's power of appointment. A
majority vote consists of more than 50%
of voting members present at a meeting
in which a quorum is established. For
the HCA board member, they may appoint a
proxy to attend and vote in their place
so long as this proxy appointment is
indicated in writing to the chair in
advance of the meeting.
Members who are not public employees are
eligible for portm and mileage
reimbursement pursuant to the PDM and
mileage act.
Any questions regarding the section 3
membership and voting eligibility?
Okay. And the next section, the open
meetings requirement. Um, all meetings
of the board shall be open to the
public. Meetings shall be announced on
the DO medical psilocybin program web
page or its successor page which is
https colon/www.n
nmth.orgabout
slashmcppab
slash. The board shall meet at least
twice per year. Meetings must be must be
announced at least three calendar days
in advance and the agenda must be posted
on the do medical psilocybin program
website at least one calendar day prior
to the meeting. And just as a note, this
next section was the part that was
brought up about the emergency clause,
and I have not finished writing it as a
draft, but I will in a moment. It is in
the event an emergency meeting called by
the chair and confirmed with the
majority of the board members through
email. The announcement time period is
waved so long as and it will be language
such as uh so long as uh a good faith
effort is made to uh announce this to
the public.
Meetings may be held in person or
virtually as stated in the public
announcement.
Any questions or comments regarding to
this.
Okay. And I did finish that language for
that uh for section part five on that.
Um but I'll move on to section five.
Selection and removal of chair and vice
chair. The chair shall be elected by a
simple majority of board members at a
meeting with a quorum. The chair is
responsible for conducting meetings. The
chair may be re removed from the
position of chair by a majority of the
board at a meeting with a quorum. A vice
chair shall be elected by a simple
majority at a meeting with a quorum
subject to secretary approval. The oh
and I believe we had actually stricken
that part. Am I correct? Okay. Uh I will
remove that.
The vice chair shall conduct meetings in
the absence of the chair.
>> Dominic Chris has a question.
>> Oh yes, Chris.
Oh, Chris, you're still on mute.
Sorry.
I feel like we should add that back in.
And I feel like the secretary should be
a part of this, but that's just me.
>> I don't agree with that. The medical
psilocybin advisory board is meant to be
a quasi independent organization and
therefore intraorganizational
business I believe should be handled
within the board.
You need to call for a vote for other
board members opinions.
>> I supported the idea that of us being
semi-independent and uh and not needing
to to seek the that that change.
And uh from my standpoint, I'm kind of
the same way. This is independent. I do
believe that the secretary does have the
ability to remove any of us at any time,
you know, for for reason. But so
therefore, there is kind of the ultimate
that the secretary does hold on that.
>> I also um agree the independence mainly
because we already established that we
all voted for the chair already. it
would kind of like take away that. Um,
we already established that with a
president.
>> Agree. We we need a little bit of that
hierarchy there to keep it the way it
needs to be.
HCA will be in the minority here and
agree with Chris on his recommendation.
Uh so just so everybody is aware uh I
I'm not sure who had said it. I think it
was Dan but uh I may be mistaken in that
but it does come down to the secretary
does have the ability to appoint and
remove board members at any time. So it
is a little bit um you know extra as far
as that approval but uh it does also
give um it is not something uh from the
standpoint of the department that it
could be either way and that would be up
to the board itself. So just to make
sure everybody knows that aspect.
>> Dominic um just to clarify what you
said. So, in essence, it it's uh kind of
redundant in some ways to have that the
vice chair picks I mean that the
secretary picks the vice chair based on
the fact that she already has the uh uh
power to be able to boot any one of us
out at that point is kind of what you're
saying.
>> Uh thank you Despa. Yes, essentially I
mean it's still the regardless the board
would be choosing or selecting the vice
chair. So it would just be with
confirmation of the secretary. But um
that's you know again the secretary does
have the ability to either appoint or
remove individuals as uh as deemed
needed.
Any other discussion on this or
Ian
or shall I continue reading?
>> Uh yeah, I think you can continue
reading. Um
>> if you guys want, we can take a vote on
the whether the secretary should affirm,
but I think from our discussion, it
seems like the majority of us are fine
with it just being within the board.
>> Okay. Um yeah, you can go ahead and move
on. Okay. And uh the next item on that
was the vice chair shall conduct
meetings in the absence of the chair and
the vice chair may be removed from the
position of vice chair by a majority of
the board at a meeting with a quorum.
Any other questions, concerns or
discussions about section five?
>> I actually had a question. Um
>> Mhm.
>> So in a lot of organizations
um the chair typically doesn't vote.
Do we still want the chair to have the
ability to vote in this meeting or would
you guys prefer um their vote be removed
since they are responsible for
conducting the meeting and debate?
I wonder if it uh on a lot of the other
boards that I'm on, the chair has a vote
only if there's a tie. I don't know if
that would be something to consider.
>> I would be perfectly okay with only
voting in the event of a tie. Um I do
think it is a bit over
powerful to both conduct the meeting and
then you also get a say in the final
decision of the board. Um it seems
a little dicey but I will 100% yield to
the majority opinion.
Um, I kind of feel like there's so few
of us that it would be helpful to have
everyone included in the vote. And I am
only a part of one other organization
and the chair has a vote.
>> Okay. And I did put
>> Oh, go ahead, Chris. Sorry.
>> I think we're all here for a reason. So,
I think everybody should
>> uh perfect. And it does work. We have an
odd number and there's an odd number set
in the statute. So, yeah, that would
work.
Okay.
Okay. Any other discussion regarding
selection and removal of chair and vice
chair?
Okay. Establishment and amendment of
bylaws. The board may establish or amend
these bylaws by a vote of at least
twothirds of the members present at a
meeting with a quorum.
Any questions, comments, discussion?
Okay. Recommendations. Oh, Chris,
>> do we want to change that to a simple
majority as well or should we leave this
as 2/3?
>> Personally, this one I do feel should
receive that super majority just because
you are kind of changing the way that
the board would operate in this way. So
this personal I would just say to have
that twothirds
>> because it is kind of a weightier
decision to make there.
>> I can agree with that.
>> Any other
>> okay with that? I just wanted to ask the
question.
>> Okay.
>> No, we appreciate your clarification.
Thank you.
Um, on top of that clarification,
the two/3s is essentially almost the
same anyway to some degree.
>> True.
>> With us,
any other discussion for this section or
shall I move on? Okay. Uh, section
seven, recommendations and official
board actions. Only appointed members of
the board who are present at a meeting
can propose or vote on official actions.
After the board adopts a recommendation,
medical psilocybin program staff shall
forward the recommendation to the
secretary for consideration
and any questions with regard to this
committees. The board may establish
committees by a majority vote of the
board. The board shall designate a chair
for each subcommittee. Uh, pardon me
everyone. I'm just going to clean up the
language since the decision was made to
call it committees. I'll just change
that to committees. On each of these
committees must have specific defined
tasks. Committees may be disbanded by a
majority of the board of a majority vote
of the board or upon completion of the
task. Each committee must report back to
the board upon completing its assigned
task.
Any questions with regard to this
section?
Chris,
>> should we change this just to the
majority vote of
um the board because I I feel like
completion of the task may become
um subjective.
So when I had imagined it uh what I mean
by upon completion of the task is um we
are creating committees for things like
um propagation rules right once they
finish with what their recommendations
are for propagation
um and we approve it then they have
completed their task. we no longer need
to get that committee re um done unless
we are planning on changing it at which
point we would assign a new committee.
Um but we just wanted to make sure that
um we weren't creating
a perpetual
um just list of
recommendations and then the board gets
overburdened with um you know things
that maybe are outside of our scope or
um not within our powers to do. I
definitely could see us removing it. Um,
I wouldn't have too much of an
objection. I just wanted to kind of
explain my reasoning behind it.
>> Chris, your hand is still raised. Was it
just continuation or did you have
another comment?
>> Um, no. I'm just taking in what Ian said
and I'm um not opposed to it either way.
Again, I'm just asking the question.
>> Um,
I feel that like maybe in terms of the
language, just for the sake of
clarification on Chris's point, would it
be something like affirming affirming
with the board completion of the task or
something to that effect?
I think we I would be fine with just um
striking the completion of the task
because we already said that the
committee must report back to the board
upon completing its task. So, I mean, if
the board decides that they're done with
their work, we can always just disband
it um on a later session because we're
going to have to have a meeting anyway
to either adopt or reject the
committee's recommendations.
>> Yeah. I guess what I'm saying is I I see
I see the uh I I hear what you're saying
as far as like uh
steps, you know, it's based on steps,
you know, first this, then this, then
that, and then this happens. And I and I
get that. I was just trying to figure
out a way to make sure that that was in
place and just um closing out that, you
know, it's affirming. It doesn't have to
change. I just wanted to like uh verify
that it's more like once this task is
completed then we move on to the next
step then this is the final you know
disbanding andor of dissolution of the
committee
procedural I guess is what I was trying
to look for. Yeah, and I completely
agree um that we want to make sure that
because the original language, you're
right, doesn't say whether they think
they completed the task or whether we
think they completed the task. So, um I
would be that's why I said I would be
good with just saying it's a majority
vote of the board to disband because
anytime we get those committee
recommendations, we're going to have to
have a meeting to either accept or deny
them. And then at that meeting we can
say okay this committee needs to rem
because we can't do this or we can say
you know what they did a great job um
they don't need to rem um as often or
maybe um we can disband the committee as
a whole depending on the situation.
So to clarify the language then do you
feel that just what uh Dominic's got
highlighted there could be removed and
we would be okay with having four read
committees may be disbanded by a
majority vote of the board
>> I see several headnods. Shall I delete
that phrase?
Okay.
Other comments, questions, discussion
regarding committees.
Okay. Conflict of interest. Uh conflict
of interest. Appearances of conflict of
interest shall be managed through
disclosure of all organizational and
professional affiliations of board
members. Board members affirm that they
hold no financial conflicts of interest
related to psilocybin production,
distribution, or clinical service
delivery. If a board member develops the
conflict of interest, they shall notify
DO immediately and resign their
position. Um, I will pause now, but
there was a question in the chat
actually about this, so I'll address
that at this point. Um, it is
specifically about financial conflicts
of interest, which means for example, a
provider could be and a health care
provider specifically or behavioral
health could be engaged in work
regarding this. they just cannot be
gaining having financial gain uh with
regard to that. So in other words cannot
have an ownership in a business or a
practice that is specifically
uh aimed towards psilocybin. Now it can
still be um and an individual could
still have financial ownership in a
practice for example that is doing other
psychotherapy, doing other psychedelic
treatments, just specifically not
psilocybin treatments that are regulated
through this program. And again, that
would include things such as somebody
having part ownership in a cultivation
or production facility uh and so forth
on that.
So hopefully that clarifies that point.
I just want to clarify something because
I am the president of Dcrim for
Psychedelics of New Mexico and I just
wanted to uh it's nonprofit. So I just
wanted to um uh have um you know some
transparency there um but I have no uh
financial interest well finance interest
in in the organization. I I just run it
as as need be to um give information to
the community and provide resources out
there that's presently existing here in
New Mexico.
>> And thank you Brenda for stating that
because that is the perfect example of
exactly this that we're talking about.
You are doing and providing services in
this field in this area. have that
knowledge, that expertise, have that
understanding of the communities
involved, but do not have that financial
interest. And that specifically is the a
issue of that financial issue or that
financial conflict being a problem. And
you do not have that because you don't
have that financial issue. So that is
exactly it. And you're declaring it,
which is the first part on here. Um and
uh and so again, I just hope that that
helps clear up this concern and this
question. And in fact uh for anybody who
is interested that is listening in, we
do welcome health care providers who are
interested in this and engaging again as
long as they do not have that financial
interest in this. And as we do have two
other board positions that are open that
we're seeking individuals to fill. Um
this is a reminder to everyone that you
can actually find the application and
what the process is on the program
website. And uh we are continuing to
accept applications until we do have all
board positions filled. Sorry, I have to
have to give that plug when have the
ability. We want to cast a wide net.
Anyway, uh back to the section about
conflict of interest for the bylaws. Any
additional questions, concerns?
>> No, that is the end of the bylaws. So,
oh, I'm sorry, Chris.
Um should there be a mechanism in here
for us to
um
remove someone if there is a perceived
or a a question about this? you know,
ethics can get
very um
subjective sometimes, I think, and is
and if somebody is not willing to
immediately resign their position and
that I would assume that we'd be relying
on the secretary to remove somebody at
that point without language stating
otherwise. Right.
>> That is correct, Chris. And you actually
don't need that specifically in the
bylaws for that very reason. Um the
conflict of interest form that all
applicants do sign does state that if a
conflict does occur that that not only
will you resign but also or that a board
member would resign but also that the
secretary has the ability to remove the
individual um which they have already.
So uh that would be the case. Um, from
my stance, I don't feel that it's
necessary at that point to add in a
separate area because uh that would be
something where the program and the
secretary would act at that point once
it was raised up. Despa
>> um question about uh going back to the
committees. Um, should there be language
in there that clarifies how the
committees will be formed, how many, or
just kind of um, you know, where we're
where we're creating these committees
from? Um, and also I I think I'm sorry I
was late earlier. Um, and then also,
were we going to have chairs for these
committees or anything like that? does I
mean does that need to be established in
the bylaws or is that just something
that we're um going to deal with
otherwise?
>> So I believe I can answer this. Um so
the board designates a board member to
serve as the chair as the nonpartial
um regulator of the committee's group.
But we know as a department and as well
as a board that the community has so
much more information than any of our
seven minds can
have alone. So, what we're planning on
doing is opening those committees up to
the expertise of the community, having a
a board member oversee that committee,
and then um those recommendations would
get propagated up to the board, and then
we would have final say. So, they would
each have a chair um
for them that's established in the
bylaws. And we have um a specific
document later in this meeting that will
talk about the specific um committee
structure committees that we are going
to create and at that time we can decide
for um chairs of those committees.
>> Okay. Yeah. I just wasn't sure if it
needed to be in this specific how that
was going to be formed but um Okay.
Thanks.
>> Okay. Any other questions or concerns
>> or discussion?
>> Okay, I hand it back. Oh, sorry, Chris.
>> I just keep stepping on you today,
Dominic. I'm sorry.
>> Anytime, Chris.
>> I just wanted to say I appreciate you
all for slowing taking the time to slow
down and go through this with me. I I
feel like we're moving too fast in a lot
of ways. And so I'm very uh grateful for
just
um taking things
slowly and uh being intentional about
this process.
>> Yeah. And if I may also I appreciate you
asking those kind of questions and
really digging into it because it's
something really important to get
everybody on this consensus. So thank
you Chris for doing it. You don't slow
it down. you don't, you know, bring
anything up that's not on people's
minds. So, thanks for doing that.
>> Yeah. And even I may have drafted these,
but I am fully ready for you guys to
tear it apart, put whatever you um think
is best in there and and make the
changes that you were your expertise got
you appointed for. So, um I have no
objection to that. Please take your
time, ask all the questions. I love
listening to how different minds
interpret the same language. So, um,
it's never a burden on us. We appreciate
your input.
>> So, at this time, I'd like to turn it
back over to you, Ian, as the chair and
uh uh since we've reviewed these um
bylaws fully, and it is up to you and
the board as to how to proceed with
either adoption or otherwise.
So, the proposed bylaws have been
discussed. At this time, we do need
formal board action. Is there a more
motion regarding adoption of the bylaws?
>> I motion to adopt them.
>> Perfect. And a second.
>> Perfect.
>> I third it.
>> Fourth it.
>> All right. I'm going to call roll. Um,
and that way we can get the votes. So,
Dan Jennings,
>> I vote I.
>> Chris Besusi,
>> uh, approve.
>> Brenda Bard,
>> I
>> Desba,
>> yes.
>> Larry,
>> approved.
>> And Alana's representative.
>> On behalf of Alana, I approve.
The motion passes and we can now get
moving on toward board priorities. Um,
for this one, I had started typing up a
draft, but I can't make the priorities
for all of us. I don't know what all of
our priorities were. So, I would like to
open um the board to discussion on what
our priorities should be.
If I can go first, I'd like to say I I
think our biggest priority should be
community community engagement. Um I
disagree with Dominic. I think we should
be out talking to people face to face in
person at this even at this time of
year. um to uh get the pulse on how
everybody's feeling about this uh in a
maybe a little less formal uh arena than
these board meetings where they're
primarily just listening sessions and uh
I think we need to establish the
committees as soon as possible
>> and you can speak Dominic.
>> Thank you Ian and Chris. We are not in
disagreement on that. I was simply
recommending it for these particular
board meetings because we have people
around in various parts of the state and
travel can be difficult as we actually
saw last week. As far as the committee
meetings, I actually would encourage you
all to have those um not just virtually
because I think that's important so
people around the state can participate
but also to have them in person and to
meet with people in person. That is
extraordinarily important and is really
a a a key highlight of us engaging with
the community overall. So, we're not
actually in disagreement on that at all.
Sorry if it seemed that way.
>> This is Larry. I wanted to mention I I I
think this is appropriate. Um there's a
community engagement process um
involving um uh both the the program and
the pilots at UNM that um is having
meetings with the focus groups
particularly vets first responders woman
of sexual trauma indigenous people. Um
if that's I'm going to post that uh that
flyer up in the uh um up in the chat so
people see that. That's just another way
for people to um get information that
will be uh then shared publicly.
>> All right. So, other than patient
engagement, another one that I would
like I mean community engagement,
another one that I would like to place a
lot of emphasis on is patient safety. Um
I believe that is all of our priorities
is making sure that we're not causing
more harm with this
Um,
does anyone other than community
engagement, does anyone else have a
priority they would like to add?
>> Uh, yes. Add something. Yeah. Oh, sorry.
>> Um, uh, yes. Um, I think training for
our providers and people that are
non-providers is going to be essential
in establishing what we need to do here
with, um, the do. Uh, what is that going
to look like? Um, I know you, Larry, uh,
you have already have things established
there at UNM, uh, protocols and
procedures, safety, uh, qualifications
for patients, dosages, and, uh, those
kinds of things. But looking at what
training looks like, we already have
that here in New Mexico. Um, what does
that look like when, uh, other people
are certified in other states that come
here to practice? uh how do we
grandfather them in uh those those kinds
of things. I don't want to get too much
into the details here, but I want to
make sure that um New Mexico has uh what
we need in order to provide for our um
patients and citizens as far as
education and procedures go.
>> Perfect. Um does anyone else have
anything to add?
Just wanted to make sure cultivation was
included.
>> Uh yeah, you and uh Dan had recommended
uh grower production requirements. Um
all right. So if there is no other
discussion, I move to adopt community
engagement, patient safety, provider
training, and grower/producer
requirements as the board's priorities
for 2026.
>> Oh, uh what did you need? Just one one
question and it might be worth just
delineating when patient safety is a a
broad a broad brush and maybe you just
want to leave it that broad brush and
and drill down on it further. Are you
talking like clinical screening
characteristics? You know, if they have
pretty bad CV or cardiovascular disease,
they may not be a great candidate
initially to start with versus like
selection of the
and please forgive me, it's my first
time here if I use the wrong the wrong
term, the person who's going to be
sitting with them during the experience
or those two individuals. what sort of
screening and training do we have to
make sure that they're uh the patient is
safe during that vulnerable encounter or
for that vulnerable period. So just
maybe defining that a little bit maybe
leave it broad here but probably want to
>> patient safety can touch up define that.
>> Yeah. So these are going to be very
broad priorities in general. We have
more um specifics when we get into that
committee document um that we can
provide. These are just kind of our
overarching
what are the board's priorities for at
least 2026 and what can we get done. So,
um, keeping them broad kind of helps us
out a little bit because it allows us to
do our our work in our individualized
um, perspectives whether you're on the
propagation committee to still be
considering things like, okay, let's get
the community involved. Let's get
patient safety done. Let's make sure
that our grower requirements are good.
Let's make sure that um even from the
production element that we know what
we're providing our providers so that
they know how to adequately create a
safe and comfortable space.
>> Uh Desba.
>> Yep. So just just I think this may or
may not fall under the outreach but I
think it's also important to just
realize how we would be able to um
recommend and or work with the tribes in
the potential
bridging of that gap. They are a
sovereign entity in the state and we
have the 23 um recognized federal tribes
here. Um but I see that similar issue in
the film industry of how do they also
get benefit and or be able to maintain
their sovereignty um and establishing
their care especially since we have like
the Indian hospitals that are funded
through the different tribes etc. It may
be difficult, but I feel like we need to
just kind of have I don't want to say on
the back of our minds, but have that be
a part of the discussion in included in
the outreach of how do we maintain
sovereignty at the same time be able to
be a bridge in creating the pathway and
the doorway for that discussion for them
to have um within their own tribe uh you
know uh sovereignty establishment. Um
yeah. So,
>> so I can definitely we can add um equity
and access as one of our priorities. I
do think it's very important that we um
listen to and take in advice from the
tribes. They have a lot of specific
healthcare needs and if we can address
those while respecting their sovereignty
and cultural heritage, I I believe that
that would be definitely a priority for
the board. Um, so would you be okay with
calling that equity and access or did
you have a better phrase than I do?
>> No, I I think that that's kind of like a
broad term, but making sure that that
stays in there as well. Um, because it
could, you know, we are trying to look
at broad. We are trying to look at how
this can be um
taken into other other states may be
able to have to to deal with this. I
think that New Mexico is the largest one
for a lot of indigenous tribes, but we
don't know what Oklahoma is is going to
do. We don't know what any of these
other states are going to potentially do
and the work that we do, people can
build on that.
>> Yeah, I think that's incredibly
important and given that the state of
New Mexico has um one of the highest
populations of indigenous persons that
we have an obligation to serve our
community and to learn from um
these cultures and how to best provide
culturally competent care. Thank you.
All right.
Any other discussion?
All right. Hearing none, um I would
entertain a motion to set community
engagement, patient safety, provider
training, grower requirements, and
equity and access as our priorities for
2026.
I second.
>> All right. Any objections?
Without objection, the motion is passed.
All right. And now we can get on to
committee formation. Uh Dominic, if you
would mind pulling that up for us.
>> Absolutely. Ian, give me just a moment
to get it on screen.
Uh, is it showing now?
>> Yes.
>> Okay, perfect.
>> And then would you mind reading it for
us?
>> Absolutely.
Um, although I have to admit, give me
just a moment to take a drink. I didn't
realize I was going to be doing quite as
much talking today.
All right. Um, the proposed committee
structure, patient qualification and
safety committee. Purpose, ensure that
psilocybin services in New Mexico are
grounded in scientific evidence,
appropriate safety standards, and
clinically sound screening criteria.
Responsibilities. Recommend to the board
the conditions or symptom clusters that
may benefit from psilocybin services.
Review and evaluate petitions for adding
or modifying qualifying conditions or
contraindications.
Recommend patient safety and exclusion
criteria including medical and
psychiatric red flag conditions,
medication interaction concerns,
stability requirements prior to
facilitation.
And similar to the uh the previous
document, I will pause after each
particular committee proposal uh to see
if there's questions, concerns.
Okay, seeing none, I'll move to the next
committee. Dosage administration and
clinical practice committee responsible
for purpose develop educ evidence-based
oh I'm sorry develop evidenceinformed
recommendations on psilocybin dosing
administration procedures and
facilitator training standards
responsibilities recommend dosage ranges
and administration protocols appropriate
for medical psilocybin use based on
updated scientific literature recommend
standards for practitioner er
competencies required training and
education supervision and scope of
practice. Recommend session structure
guidance including preparation duration
and environmental conditions and
integration expectations.
Analyze current clinical research and
data to define clear dosage parameters
including minimum effective doses and
maximum safety limits for various
therapeutic or consumer applications.
Identify risk factors,
contraindications, and side effect
profiles associated with specific dosage
levels to ensure public safety and
informed consent. Establish a process
for the periodic review of emerging
scientific literature and realworld data
to adjust dosage recommendations as the
field evolves.
And that's the end of that committee
section. So I'll pause for any
discussions, comments, or concerns.
Dominic, I have I have a comment or or
question. Um um it mentions required
training and education. Would this be
the committee that would be looking at
like what type of a training programs
are acceptable? Are we doing reciprocity
with um other states? Is that would that
be this committee or a different
committee?
>> Uh that is up to this board.
>> I might suggest a different committee.
>> Sorry.
>> I'm sorry. I it's a it's a big thing. So
I you know the the the training part is
a big thing. So it might make sense to
have it as a separate committee. Oh,
>> Larry, you you were saying uh um
with basically people that have had
previous chain training like for
instance in other states could um
qualify for um more training here.
>> Yeah, I I I I I think I think that's a
question. I mean, I think that um if we
are trying to get a program up quickly,
um one of the one of the delays in other
states is establishing a training
program. So, if we're requiring training
and people could get reciprocity from
Colorado or Oregon, that may um that may
facilitate the process, but but I wasn't
trying to get into the weeds here. I was
just trying to decide which committee
would be looking looking at that.
>> Yeah, because that that that has also
been on my mind, too. And I just wanted
to let you know that as well because
there are a lot of people that have come
to me and said, "Hey, I've been trained
uh in, you know, other states and it's
incredibly pricey." So, yes, of course.
Um I I think that should be uh something
to look at as far as a committee goes.
Uh Dan,
>> Dan,
>> no, I see that the uh Dominic's already
moving it. I was just going to make a
recommendation if that might just be
moved out so that that way this
particular subcommittee that you're
looking at focuses only on the the the
environment kind of a dosing and then we
separate that out and committee, but it
looks like they're already doing it. So,
>> perfect. Yeah, I would be amendable to
that. Uh Kenan
Mine is on a separate topic. So if
there's further discussion on that, I
suggest going to that and then I'll
bring up my my point of clarification.
>> Is anyone opposed to separating them?
>> No. Okay, cool.
>> I'm I'm curious how
I guess binding this document is. Do we
need to really get into the weeds on um
language and the purpose? Uh it it's it
seems like it might be restrictive at
various points unless we're really
careful. But this is ultimately these
committees are just being formed for
generally these reasons and um the
recommendations that come out of them
don't have to necessarily fall strictly
within these guidelines. Is is that how
I'm understanding this?
>> Right. So, what I did when making these
committees was go through um Senate Bill
219 and see what our specific
responsibilities as the board were and
then kind of space them out to be in
separate sections.
I imagined that the clinical practice
and dosing and administration would be
together because I figured that the
experts would be the same for those
settings. So, I had just said, "Okay,
it's going to be providers, it's going
to be um clinicians, uh therapists, that
kind of thing setting those standards."
And I figured those were the same
experts I would want to set dosing. Um
so, I had imagined them together. I have
no objection to separating them. Um
but that's kind of where my headspace
was at. Um it is kind of binding on the
fact that the committee can't only
derives power from what we say they have
the power to do. Um
so that part is a little bit binding. Uh
Desba
>> I just kind of wanted to go back because
I think I might have missed something um
in regards to another question that I
saw in the chat. You know what is the
what is the role of the facilitator? And
I know that this might be getting ahead,
but to me there is
uh you know, for lack of a better way of
explaining, western medicine and then
this like indigenous ancestral west uh
eastern medicine, right? So there's
these two kind of things. Um so it seems
to me that separating them would kind of
be where we could have that area between
the clinicians, the medical such as
yourself as a nursing student. Then we
also have the people who h are not from
a medical background but have been
working with the medicine for a long
time and understand you know certain
protocols that we can share that
information.
Is that kind of where we're trying to
hope that these committees for education
and training and facilitation
um medical providers can be able to have
that ability to to share that knowledge
um and be able to have that reciprocity.
Is that getting too far into the weeds
or is that kind of where I'm thinking
that it sounds like we're all trying to
make sure that we have the space for
those types of discussions in the
future?
>> Yeah, absolutely. Um, so what I had
envisioned, um, and Dominic actually
scrolled down to it was the equity,
access, and cultural considerations
committee would have recommended
policies that ensure culturally
appropriate practices for indigenous and
Hispanic communities as those are the
two that have historically used the
medicine. um that way they could set
their own precedent for how to use it
because as someone who's very I guess
involved in western medicine I don't
think it's right of me to speak on
recommendations for indigenous tribes or
indigenous peoples and that's why I kind
of separated them out because I was like
there can be uh a very religious and
culturally sensitive and historical
version of the program where we can uh
work with the indigenous tribes to
provide those medicines in compliance
with their culture versus a very rigid
western medical system where we're like
okay
we have different cultural expectations
we like you know the doctor and the
nurse and therapist but that may not be
always applicable to um someone's
inherent beliefs so um that's where I
kind of differentiated them but if you
would like them to be together, then
separating those two committees
definitely allows for their voice to be
louder in that um the western medicine
side as well, which could be very
helpful.
>> Yeah, I just was kind of making sure I I
feel like there's definitely a place
where we can all have that cross
educational um knowledge, you know,
because I hear it loud and clear, you
know, that we're taking the spirit of
the medicine, etc., etc., But I
understand the need for regulation etc.
and being able to understand quality of
dosages etc. So it's just it's good to
have it separate but I also wanted just
to make sure that you know we're um
that that was where my mind was as far
as like being able to educ co-educate
each other and that there wasn't
necessarily like
this huge divide
um in in thought.
>> Yeah. I'm just gonna hop in here because
I have I agree with what you're saying,
Desba. I I also think you should keep
them in I would not I agree with the
structures proposed. Now, let me put it
that way. Um specifically looking at
equity and access, but I think we can
learn from each other and keeping all of
those in the clinical group or clinical
dosage uh group together. Um I think
it's important. I would add to that that
I want to make sure
while this is a medical psilocybin work
group that the the
true work comes after right when in the
therapy and the the wraparound services
that really need to make sure are
provided there. So there is one line in
that first committee group about
integration. I just would like to make
sure that it's clearly defined as a
requirement that it's not just the
dosing of the psilocybin, but actually
the the entirety of the this is a
multimodal service, right? It's both
about the psilocybin dosage to make sure
it's clinically effective, but that's
what really opens up so that the the
therapy and the counseling and all that
other work that really has to come after
it is is effective, right? And so that's
what we're really doing. So making sure
that's included. So it's not just the
dosing but also what's the standard for
for engagement with therapy afterwards
that we would recommend as best practice
and is that group therapy as that's
individual therapy. There's models for
both. I get that but really making sure
we have that included in this
committee's group would be my
recommendation.
So we do have um that the dosage and
administration will recommend session
structure with guidance, preparation,
duration and environmental conditions as
well as integration expectations. Um so
I believe it fulfills what you're asking
for. Um, but if are you saying you would
like that to be separate or
>> I think what I was misreading session
structure uh as like how frequently they
were going to be dosed like every six
months or something. So, as long as it's
clear that the the expectations for
those wraparound services are really
there, I'm fine with it as is. If that's
how the rest of the board reads it, I'm
fine.
Uh, and then Chris,
>> I'm sorry. I I I think I forgot what my
question was. I'll let you all carry on.
>> No worries. And then Dominic.
>> Yeah. I I just want to clarify for
everybody is this is really just meant
not as a a beall endall document. This
is really uh something just saying these
are the areas and topics that these
committees are going to be looking at.
there definitely is going to be um need
for crosswork between different
committees and among different
committees and uh so one of the things
that I would really recommend is that
some of the individuals that are on
these different committees as they are
announced and posted which um you know
will be open to the public to be able to
attend and participate you know will
probably end up being on or attending
multiple committees. We just want to
make sure that each committee really has
at least an idea of these are the areas
that they need to look at. And there
will definitely be things that either
get added in or may say as as the
committees start meeting may say, you
know, oh, this really should go to this
committee rather than this one. And
that's okay. This is really just an idea
and a starting place um as far as what
committees are established. And then as
they continue to progress, it can be
refined as to what areas and uh uh
sections and parts of rules,
regulations, and recommendations that
they are going to focus on. Thank you.
>> Yeah, and to piggyback, it's it's a
simple majority to change, so it's not
like it's set in stone. Um but Larry had
a question or point.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Just one recommendation
actually deals with what was brought up
before where it says recommend session
structure. I would change that to
recommend therapeutic structure um to to
be bit more expansive on that. I I I
agree with Dom. I mean we don't have to
get too into the granular but I think
that would be an important change on
wording.
>> That's fine with me.
>> Okay. Is there additional discussion
regarding this particular committee?
Okay. And I did separate out the
education and training and just broke
that out into several uh points which
are recommend standards for practitioner
competencies, recommend required
training and education and recommend
supervision requirements and scope of
practice. And again the committees can
actually add items to this. This is just
the start.
Any
questions, concerns here?
Okay. Propagation committee purpose.
Ensure that New Mexico psilocybin
production aligns with safety, quality,
and testing standards. Responsibilities.
Recommend best practices for psilocybin
mushroom cultivation, harvesting,
drying, storage, and contamination
control standards. Recommend lensure
criteria for producers, manufacturers,
and laboratories. Recommend to the full
board rules on production, purity,
potency, labeling, and packaging
standards. Monitor national and
international research on product safety
and testing innovations. Recommend
updates as needed.
Any questions or concerns? And I'll
pause for a few moments.
I have a qu um again I know we're not
trying to get into the weeds and
anything um
this is probably where I feel like in
addition to the this is like the um
consumer provider side money side of
things for sure I mean I know that
there's money in the medical research
but you know is there any need to add
the financial aspect of like
I don't know I just know this is going
to be very costly just from the research
I've done as far as um you know being
able to have like who's going to pay for
the
testing and you know is it going to be
able to be available and accessible for
the for the cultivators to be able to
have that especially for for if we're
trying to just make it for New Mexico. I
know that there's lots of testing, lots
of money in different places for private
uh corporations to do their clinical
trials, but you know, I'm thinking about
the New Mexico growers and such. So, I
don't know if that needs to be in here,
but that's just my concern.
>> And Desba, that actually is a part of it
with regard to especially the national
and international research on product
safety and testing innovations. I would
see that the financial aspect of that
would be wrapped up in there. Um but uh
again I mean if we need to add you know
I can actually just include um including
uh financial
uh aspects.
I would instead of doing that I would
add another point that says ensuring
um
testing
is not
financially cumbersome as in it's going
to
we are going to have to essentially
create not create but the state market
is going to have to create laboratory
and um other factors in order to
facilitate
um
you know the market and I want to ensure
that you know all of the testing that
we're doing while the market is still
small does not encumber on the on the
product as a whole and I can see where
Desba is thinking of that because
especially in rural New Mexico we to
have them develop and create testing
centers I don't think is a realistic uh
possibility. So um
making sure that we can maintain
patients safety while also not giving
them unnecessary tests that would make
it financially burdensome would be very
good. Thank you Desba.
So I did add on in uh the point saying
ensuring testing recommendations are as
affordable as possible while requiring
uh measures necessary for patient
safety.
Okay. Additional comments, concerns,
discussion regarding propagation.
Okay, the next one is equity access and
cultural consideration committee.
Purpose ensure that New Mexico's medical
psilocybin services system is
accessible, culturally appropriate and
responsive to the needs of indigenous
rural frontier, Hispanic, and
underserved communities and that program
implementation promotes equity,
inclusion, and culturally grounded care
across all settings. responsibilities.
Recommend to the board policies to
expand access to rural frontier and
underserved areas of New Mexico,
including but not limited to teleaalth
enabled screening and rural training.
Recommend anti-discrimination and
anti-stigma policies within the psiloc
psilocybin services system. Recommend
policies that ensure culturally
appropriate practices for indigenous and
Hispanic communities.
Uh Dan,
>> I just wanted to ask if this might be a
good place to put the acquisity because
of the financial
um parts that it would be for
uh as a patient that was not covered
under insurance at the moment of course
and who knows in the future. the fact
that we want to make sure that this is
accessible to people financially. Um, I
don't know if that makes sense to put it
into this, but also accessible for uh
prioritizing New Mexicans specifically.
I don't know if this is something to
bring up on this committee or not, but I
just wanted to ask
Uh so what I went ahead and I just added
in ple uh just sort of as general is
determine qualifications and
determinations for eligibility of
financial assistance through the patient
equity fund.
I think that sort of addresses it.
Although I may slightly change the
language so I don't say determination
twice.
>> Thank you for that.
Okay. Any other discussion for this
area?
>> Okay. Um moving on to the end of life
care committee. Purpose ensure that
psilocybin services for individuals
experience serious illness, lifelimiting
conditions or end of life distress are
delivered safely, ethically and in
accordance with best practices in
palative care, supportive care and
traumainformed approaches. This
committee will support the development
of guidelines that promote dignity,
comfort, cultural respect, and
evidenceinformed care for patients
receiving psilocybin during advanced
illness and end of life transitions.
Responsibilities recommend clinical and
ethical guidance for psilocybin use in
individuals experiencing serious illness
or end of life distress. recommend
safety criteria, screening
considerations and interdisciplinary
coordination practices to end of life
care, including collaboration with
palative care providers, hospice
agencies, behavioral health clinicians,
and spiritual or cultural support.
Recommend informed consent requirements,
advanced care planning, and
communication standards for patients and
families receiving end of life
psilocybin services.
Recommend culturally appropriate,
trauma-informed and dignity centered
care guidelines for end of life
psilocybin services.
Any questions, concerns, discussion?
No. Okay. I see lots of head nods of no
uh for additional discussion. So the
next committee is the research and
continuous improvement committee.
Ensure that practitioner preparation,
research activities, harm reduction
practices, and program evaluation for
medical psilocybin services in New
Mexico are grounded in scientific
evidence, ethical standards, and
continuous quality improvement
principles. recommend guidelines for
research and data collection, including
core data elements to be collected by
practitioners and do outcome monitoring
and adverse event reporting standards,
ethical research practices, including
considerations for tribal and culturally
specific communities evaluation
frameworks for monitoring safety,
clinical outcomes, and population level
trends.
recommend harm reduction and quality
improvement practices including risk
screening frameworks and medication
interaction guidance, emergency
preparedness and crisis response
expectations, informed consent content
and patient education materials,
mechanisms for updating clinical
training and safety standards as new
evidence emerges.
And that's the end of that particular
committee portion. Any questions,
comments, or discussion.
Okay. So that's actually the end of this
document and so I'll just very quickly
go through the specific committee names.
So they are patient qualification and
safety committee, dosage administration
and clinical practice committee,
education and training committee,
propagation committee, equity, access
and cultural considerations committee,
end of life care committee, uh and
research and continuous improvement
committee.
So, as a total, that's seven committees.
>> Perfect.
>> Which actually Oh, sorry. Go on. Sorry.
No, no. I was gonna say that's actually
perfect since there are seven board
members.
>> And then, uh, Larry had a question.
>> Yeah. I mean, more of an addendum maybe.
Um, now that we have these set up, um,
is there something that we can let
people know in the public that they can
do to apply to to be on committees?
Um
Ian
>> once we vote on it.
>> Oh yeah, go on it. Uh so uh Larry what
we've recommended from the department
and again this will be up to the board
to make a determination is we're
recommending that uh what we would do is
once the committees and the chair is
determined that at that point and a date
set for the initial committee meeting
that uh the chair from the board or
whomever is appointed as chair let us
know at the program level we will post
it and send it out through our constant
contact so through the e-update
um for in uh individuals who are
interested in attending and
participating to attend and then uh that
way it would be open to anybody who has
interest and be able to help provide
expertise and that's just what we're
recommending at that point. Um and that
way individuals would be able to find
out about it. It would be posted both on
our website and through the eupdates,
the electronic updates.
>> Perfect. Thank you. And then Desba,
>> um I did see a comment on there about
enforcement and any of these in
particular ones for the regulations um
of growing andor um facilitation. Is
there anything in there that needs to be
about enforcing these or is that come
later when in the committees?
We set up a mechanism for lensure um and
that would be the enforcement mechanism
for um the psilocybin program
but other than that if you wanted to
create something more I believe it'd
have to come from the department of
health but Dominic you can correct me if
I'm wrong.
Uh yes, enforcement with regard to the
program itself would be a part of the
compliance aspect of the program. And
for example, one of the staff positions
that we are looking at hiring is a
compliance officer. And so they would be
able to help in formulating some of
those areas uh as far as from a
regulatory standpoint as we start moving
forward in that section.
>> So that just so just to clarify for the
sake of um education. So that part of
the enforcement would come after the
formation of these committees and then
being able to to enforce it.
>> Well, I mean after after everything is
done and we're starting to go up into
establishing these things, they're up
and running. That's when that would be
uh implemented.
>> The different areas are going to have
different aspects with regard to enforce
enforcement for what are the regulations
that are recommended and then put into
place. So um so that will be a part of
the regulation formation and there'll be
parts of it probably in different
aspects of several of the committees um
for example in the the lensure and the
training and education requirements
again with regard to propagation for
cultivation testing um and so those will
be incorporated into or will need to be
incorporated into the recommendations
from those different committees and
other committees as well. Just using
those as examples.
>> Got it. Awesome. Thank you.
>> Perfect. And then Chris,
>> I'd like to also recommend a veteran and
first responders specific committee um
to look at the specific needs of that
community.
>> Any objections?
>> No. Then we can go ahead and add it.
Where would you like that added? I'm
sorry.
>> Oh, so Chris, let me ask you that. Would
you rather create an entire separate
committee or would you rather add like a
veteran specificity under the equity and
access committee?
Um,
I think I would rather have a
specific committee for that population
and then we can see what kind of comes
out of it. I I haven't fully
>> uh
>> um
if you want to create a committee, what
we can do is we can adopt these six and
then it only requ majority vote to do
the veterans committee specifically.
That way you can add the specific
language that you want in it.
>> All right. I'll I'll work with um some
people and add that language to a
proposal for our next meeting.
>> Perfect. Thank you.
>> Um Larry.
>> Yeah. And this may be a conversation
Chris and I can can have. What I I think
the veterans and the first responders is
going to have a major focus on PTSD. And
so we might try to figure out are we is
that like a you know is is PTSD in a
separate committee or just try to look
at that as you're as you're um making
the the plan for that committee. Um it
would seem like it would be key for the
PTSD diagnosis.
>> And then Desba
>> I just kind of wanted to clarify a
little with what Chris was recommending.
Um, in that case, you know, I what I'm
envisioning and how I interpreted was,
you know, even, you know, police
officers, you know, not just them, but
which has been a big issue with figuring
out how they respond to the public who
are having mental ill health crisis. Um,
so I'm not sure that's how I read it
from what Chris's perspective is how do
we can how how this could be a way to
bridge that gap as a way to move that
also forward to having more
understanding of the community that the
first responders are serving.
I'll keep that in mind as I'm coming up
with the language and maybe we can use
that committee as kind of a a bridge
between those worlds both to look at
veteran specific needs or veteran and
first responder specific needs
with the use of the medicine and um how
we can
incorporate training with local law
enforcement and uh response agencies.
All righty. Um, if there is no more
discussion, I move to or I
I would entertain a motion to adopt the
seven committees as provided.
Is there any objections?
>> I'll make a motion to approve these
seven.
>> Perfect.
>> Second.
>> Perfect. Any objections?
With unanimous consent, the committees
are formed.
Um,
we also need to designate a board member
to serve as chair for each committee.
Um, does anyone have Does anyone want to
do We'll go ahead and do them in order.
Um, does anyone want to be chair of the
patient qualification and safety
committee?
All right. Um, we can do nominations for
that one another time. How about dosage
administration clinical practice?
The education and training committee.
>> I uh I would not opposed. Is there
somebody else that wants
>> Go ahead.
>> I'm not I just do raising my hand. Uh
yeah, I think that uh I would uh like to
be part of the education training
committee. I I have another question
too. Maybe two board members could uh
possibly um maybe be on both uh or or
two committees. Would that be possible?
>> Yeah. Um you could be. Right now there's
seven committees and there are seven of
us. So each I was thinking each of us
could chair a committee, but I have no
objection to serving on more than one.
Um especially because Chris is going to
permit another committee at the next
meeting, which means we may need a
double chair. So I would have no
objection to that.
>> Okay.
>> All right. Uh so Brenda for the
education and training. Um how about for
propagation?
I would like to chair the propagation
board.
>> Okay.
>> Um, equity, access, and cultural
considerations.
>> Uh, I know Larry had recommended the end
of life committee. Would you still like
would you like to chair that one?
I I would.
>> And then uh Dan, you had recommended the
research and continuous improvement
committee. Would you like to chair that
one?
>> Yes, please. That would be great.
>> All right. And then um I can do patient
safety and qualification. Patient
qualification and safety. That was the
first one we did. Um
and then we would still need one for the
dosage administration and clinical
practice
which um if we can't come up with at
this time we can delay appointing the
chair until the next meeting.
>> This is Larry. I'm happy to help because
this is kind of my my day job a little
bit. Um, but I maybe rather not be the
the the chair of like most committees,
but I'd be happy to help if somebody
else would volunteer to eventually chair
it.
>> Yeah, I can actually volunteer to chair
patient qualification and safety.
>> Um,
all right.
And then, uh, dosage admin dosage
administration clinical practice is the
last one.
I would like to be part of that, but
um I too didn't don't want to chair, but
I'd like to um offer my um
um my services if I can um to anybody
who wants to
uh chair that.
Um,
for that one, it doesn't look like we
have a nominee, so we can just uh push
that one as being the only board we need
to still nominate someone for um at the
next meeting.
>> All right. Is there any other business
that the board members would like to
bring forward?
>> Mr. Zerlo,
>> thank you, Ian. I just want to double
check to make sure that I have
everything correct here. So I have for
patient qualification and safety
committee yourself Ian. Uh dosage and
administration is to be determined.
Education and training Brenda Burgard
chair. Uh propagation committee is
Chris. Whoops. Sorry Chris, I misspelled
your name. My apologies. Mr. E. Um and
then uh equity, access, and cultural
considerations, Desba. And Desba, I'm
sorry. Uh, how would you like your last
name listed on care?
>> Um, if I just usually just go by Desba,
but if we need to be legal, I have
>> We can we can leave it as that. I just
wanted to make sure to acknowledge it.
>> Uh, great. Thank you. Uh, end of life
care committee is Larry Leman. Uh, and
then research and continuous improvement
committee Dan Jennings. Is that correct?
Did I miss anything?
Okay, I just wanted to make sure I had
that correct before we move forward. And
just to note in the chat, some people
have asked about the documents. Yes, all
the documents, and it usually can take a
few days to a week or so for us to get
them up onto our website, but they will
be placed onto uh the advisory board
website. If you go to the advisory board
website on the left side, there's
several different subsections. One of
those is the meeting records, and we
will be putting it into those areas. But
please do give us a little bit of time
uh to work with our IT department to get
those posted. Thank you.
>> All right. Is there any other business
for the board to attend to that anyone
would like to bring forward?
>> No.
All righty. Um then we just need to
select our next meeting date and
location.
So, we can meet before the legislative
session if you guys would like or we can
defer to um
let's see, hold on, let me look at the
dates. My calendar isn't loading.
Um, so if we wanted to keep it before
the session,
we could do the 9th of January at 9:00
a.m. again if you guys would like or if
you have another suggestion.
Chris,
>> I have a conflict with that day. I'm not
sure. A different day might work that
week.
>> Yeah. Um,
we could do the Thursday of that week.
We could do the week after. It's really
>> I I could do either of that. I could
either do the Friday the 16th or or
Thursday the 15th. Um,
do people want to keep Fridays? Would
Friday the 16th be more consistent with
schedules or
>> are you available on the 8th?
>> Um, Larry,
>> um, I am after 9:00.
>> All right. The 8th works for me.
So, do you guys want to do January 8th
at 10?
>> I don't think I can make it. Um,
I would rather stick with the Friday on
the 12th at 9,
>> the
>> Monday the 12th.
>> Monday the
>> Friday the 16th.
>> Are you looking at in the following
year?
The next Friday, um, after the 9th is
the 16th.
>> And Brenda, I think you were talking and
you're on mute.
>> The 16th would be fine. At 9:00 for me,
um, during the week is kind of hard.
>> So, does the 16th at 9 work for
everyone?
16th of N works for me.
>> Okay,
>> Desba, Jen,
>> Larry.
>> All right. And Brenda,
good. Perfect. Um, do you know if uh
Lana is going to be available?
>> Don't know. That's the last day before
session starts. So, we might already be
in bill analysis mode because bills are
actually um
>> filed on the second,
>> right? So, they're just we're going to
start reviewing stuff. So, it's it's
hard to say. I'll just be honest as we
get close to session. I can uh follow up
with her at at 9ine or the the date of
nine. I'm sorry, nine on the 16th.
Correct.
>> Yeah. Let me follow up with her
>> um and I can report back. Um, I just
can't commit to anything right now.
>> All right. And then Chris, you had a
question.
>> Yeah. Um, how do we start setting up
committee meetings? Is there a formal
process for that or
um
>> feels like we have a lot of time in
between our next board meeting and the
some we could do some community
engagement in between.
>> Yeah. Uh, I think Dom has a better
answer than I do.
>> Uh, thank you, Ian and Chris. That's a
great question. I I had kind of
mentioned that once as a chair you set
your date and time, if you want to do it
virtually, let us know and we'll set up
that meeting. If you want to do it in
person, we can also help with
arrangements as far as that goes. Um and
uh so once the chair sets that, if they
get that to us here at the department,
we will then go ahead and get it set up
and send out that announcement uh both
on our website and also through the e
update so that individuals would be able
to attend.
And and hopping on to that uh same
question with the chairs and in setting
up the meetings. Um would we then now
since there is an audience that we have
here already ask for people to start
contacting the chairs about wanting to
be on specific committees and or what
would you recommend in the interim?
Uh what we would actually recommend is
that individuals who are interested
simply show up to the first meeting and
um that the chair then records it there,
create a contact list which we again as
the program will help from an
administrative standpoint and move
forward that way.
And just as sort of a reminder,
committees do not need to have a formal
membership. It's really just those are
their areas and then it's up to the
chair to sort of determine within that
committee. So like bylaws are not needed
items, you know, additional items are
not needed within the committees.
They're really workg groups to try to
get the information and moving it
forward. And so at least from the
program standpoint, we really recommend
that for individuals who are interested
in being on a committee, it's really
about participation. And so they show
up, help with it, and move forward that
way. And then also on that um you
mentioned some kind of administration um
with setting up the meetings but while
we're having the meetings do we have
someone to help us with these
administration tasks and or do we just
uh file the minutes andor the notes that
we have from the committees to our
SharePoint? How how would that re what
is that kind of uh interaction?
>> Great question Desbot. We will uh as a
program we will actually assign one of
our staff members to the committees and
as they get set up we will do so so that
uh the chair will know in advance.
>> Okay.
>> So do we make a official public
announcement to those who are especially
here to definitely contact us and do
they have our contact information? I I
also have several different emails and I
don't know if there's a preferred one
that we should use um for anyone to
contact myself or anyone else here on
the board with their interest in in
being a part of our committees.
>> Yeah, again I would recommend that it
just simply be for those individuals who
attend the committee meeting as you
started up and at that point again we'll
have staff who can then gather that
contact information. So each committee
then has a list to be able to do that.
If someone is not able to attend that
meeting, they are welcome to email us at
the main email which is
medical.silocybin
at uh dooh.nm.gov.
And the reason I would say that is again
as a reminder all of the activities of
the board members are subject to and
this way we are able to keep all of that
together without it being uh an issue
for you as the board members to be
overburdened with trying to track those
sort of items. And so that's why we do
recommend if individuals would like to
contact on it to reach out through this,
but we do recommend that it be through
that first meeting that individuals show
up and attend and that's where we can
actually create those lists for contact
for the individual committees.
>> Got it. And then just again, sorry to um
go this. So for the public their best
way of being a part of the com
committees is to wait till one of us is
uh the chairs establishes a time in a
meeting that they would like to meet.
That link will then go out to the public
and be provided on the page andor if the
public is really raring to go and wants
to be a part of something they are free
to contact the medical psilocybin uh do
uh email that was just provided in the
chat. Is that correct?
>> Yes. But I would recommend that they
attend the committee first and then if
they are not able to attend the meeting
once it is published then to reach out.
Otherwise quite frankly we would be
overwhelmed and we would not be able to
serve you as a board because we would be
responding to all of those other items.
So what we recommend is we recommend uh
that that happen once the committee
meetings are set up. Individuals who are
interested simply attend them. Um and if
they're not able to at that point they
can reach out and we will forward that
information uh and present it actually
during the committee itself.
>> Okay, great. Thank you for um clarifying
the protocol for that. Appreciate it.
>> Um also to I'm sorry I didn't raise my
hand. Also to maybe um uh having that
written out and and posted uh to our
documents too. That would be helpful.
And my question was just going to be
that if people already signed up for the
um like the newsletter blast that goes
out through the do site that if we post
our if we get our committees up then
that would go out as like an
announcement through that mechanism. So
that way if people are ready to sign up
for the email blasts they'll be notified
when these committees are going to be
meeting too.
All righty.
Um, so is there any other business?
Um,
if not, then we have a few minutes for
public comment.
Uh, and at this point I will go ahead
and I will put um the directions for how
individuals can unmute once they are
unmuted. Um, in the meantime uh Kathy
will be helping us with calling out the
individuals in the order that their hand
is raised. If you are interested in um
in providing public comment, please go
ahead and raise your hand uh in teams.
And um the way to do that if you are not
sure is if you are on a computer you
should click and sorry uh here should
have a slide showing it. Uh if on a
computer please click on the hand icon
near the top of the team windows. It
says raise underneath the icon. If you
are on the team's app on a phone please
press the ellipses which are the three
dots in the menu and then the hand icon
will appear and you can select it. And
if you are joining through voice only on
a phone, please press star five to raise
or lower your hand.
And then once uh you are called upon,
you will be able to unmute. And to
unmute, please uh on the teams on a
computer or on the phone app, click on
the microphone icon, which is the little
icon highlighted in yellow on the
screen. If you are joining us by
telephone and voice only, please press
star six to unmute or mute. I will
actually um circle through these two
slides uh as we go through public
comment. Um please remember individuals
um who are uh uh who are engaging in
public comment. You have 3 minutes to uh
to provide your comment and at the 30
second mark 30 seconds prior to the end
we will give you a warning and let you
know. Okay,
>> Kathy I think we are back.
>> We'll go to Yeah, we'll go to our first
um person uh James. Um please unmute
your line. You have three minutes.
>> Testing. Can you guys hear me? Okay.
>> Yes.
>> Thank you. My name is James Aobe and I'm
a pharmaceutical scientist from Arizona
and I've been involved in the Arizona
psilocybin research efforts including
testimony to our department of health
services and the psilocybin research
advisory council and it is an honor to
learn and be with you guys here today. A
major strength that SB 219 does is more
than authorized access. I think it
really directs the department to collect
data, publish annual assessments, and
consider rural and tribal access while
creating an equity trust or an equity
fund and a research fund. This framework
really allows us to build a system that
is safety driven and equitydriven from
the outset, which is especially
important given the ambitious timeline
here. My priority in this area is human
safety and the prevention of avoidable
harm. I personally believe psychedelics
are not appropriate for everybody and
the way the program is designed will
determine whether they reduce suffering
or inadvertently create iatrogenic
injury. With this in mind, my main
question is how does the board envision
the program's data architecture,
especially for long-term outcomes and
indigenous communities? How does the
board think of defining a minimum core
outcome set with minimum follow-up
periods that every participating site
will be expected to collect and not only
acutely but over a 6, 12 or 24month
consideration.
A safety conscious program needs to be
seen than a short-term symptom change.
It should be able to track durable uh
remission or relapse, suicidality or
self harm, emergent psychosis or mania,
or even basic quality of life outcomes.
Many of these candidates will also be on
SSRIs, SNRIs, mood stabilizers, or other
psychoactive substances. If the program
is truly safetydriven, tapering plans
and co-contaminate medication use and
potential polypharmarmacological
interactions need to be visible in the
longitudinal data and not treated as a
background noise. Within this framework,
I'm particularly interested in how
indigenous patients, members of the New
Mexico tribes, nations, and pblo will be
reflected in the data in a way that is
both analytically meaningful and
respectful to tribal sovereignty and
privacy. Will the department and this
board consider co-designing metrics,
follow-up expectations?
>> Thank you. reporting categories within
the tribes, indigenous clinicians, and
other traditional healers so that annual
assessments can show whether indigenous
patients are accessing care and how
their outcome long-term outcome changes
and where these barriers will be met.
New Mexico has a really cool opportunity
to set a national standard for
implementing medical psilocybin in a way
that is scientifically rigorous,
conservatively safe, and generally
accountable.
>> Thank you. Thank you very much for your
time.
>> Okay. Uh the next person is uh Denali
Wilson. Uh your line is activated.
Please unmute. You have three minutes.
>> Good morning board and department of
health. My name is Denali Wilson. I am
the New Mexico director of strategic
support for the healing advocacy fund,
which is a nonprofit that supports state
regulated access for psychedelic
healing. Um, I just want to express deep
gratitude for the board uh and the work
that you've put in today. I'm so
grateful to see
movements starting on some of these
priorities and especially grateful for
the board's focus on equity and
affordability. I wanted to make a quick
recommendation. Um, perhaps not
necessary or actionable at this moment
in the program, but it seems like it may
be helpful in the future to create a
subcommittee to focus on insurance and
healthcare integration specifically. Um,
that subcommittee could focus on the
pathways for Medicaid and commercial
insurance coverage. We know that there
are pieces of this care that will not be
coverable until there is FDA approval.
But um as many of you mentioned, so much
of this care model is
part of this is is therapeutic in nature
and involves practices that are already
covered by insurance, both Medicaid and
and commercial. Um but it does and will
take thoughtful um attention to to make
sure that those pathways are possible.
Um, this subcommittee could also focus
on specific issues to New Mexico as a as
a medically integrated model. I'm
thinking about the issues that are going
to arise for our providers who are also
holders of DEA prescriber licenses,
questions of professional liability um,
and other issues that may arise related
to the dual lensure nature of much of
our practitioners. So that's my
recommendation, but grateful for the
board's uh work today and especially
again the focus that uh we're witnessing
on equity and affordability.
Thank you.
Uh next we go to Shane.
Please unmute your line. You have three
minutes.
Shane.
Okay, we'll go to the next person.
Uh Paul,
please unmute your line. You have three
minutes.
>> Good morning, everyone. My name is Paul
Walton and I'm with firefighters for
plant medicine. Uh thank everyone who
worked on this and made this happen.
This is a great opportunity for New
Mexico to be leaders in this healing
treatment. Um as a firefighter uh for
Burningham County for almost 18 years.
I've witnessed and experienced firsthand
the emotional and uh physical tolls that
this job can have on individuals. Um,
our work often involves exposure to
traumatic events that can lead to
several work-related injuries such as
severe depression and PTSD. Our first
responders have a higher rate of mental
health issues and suicide rates. Uh,
this treatment can directly impact
occurrences um of suicide. We recently
had a firefighter lose a battle with
depression. Uh, there's a mental health
crisis in our first responders and in
our medical community. Yet they are
often overlooked when it comes to mental
health treatment. Uh these work-related
injuries often make normal everyday life
a struggle for first responders. These
struggles not only affect our first
responders but their families,
co-workers are in our community.
Unfortunately, first responders are
often the last to seek help due to
cultural stigmas and surrounding mental
health. We are the first to help others
but the last to help ourselves. This
stigma along with affordability and a
treatment resistance presents barriers
for first responders. Peers for first
responders and veterans is also another
important aspect to consider in these
regulations. In order to treat our first
responders, we must reach them and break
down these treatment barriers. First
responders are not normal mental health
patients and need special regulation
attention for effective treatment. We
need to be able to accommodate first
responder patients and comfort levels to
have effective treatments for them.
Another tool for address treatment
barriers could be micro doing. Having a
micro doing treatment policy could help
address some of these barriers. This
could also help with integration and
continued support after a therapeutic
dose. First responders have to go back
to work after these uh therapeutic
treatments and are subject to future
trauma. My hope is that the Department
of Health and the Advisory Board will
look at these barriers for first
responders seriously and find a way to
work with advisers to make solutions to
help our public servants. When our first
responders are mentally healthier and
happier, their family, co-workers,
employers, and the communities directly
benefit making our community safe and
healthier. Um, I appreciate you guys
working on this and um committees and
doing all this work. It's it's
>> 30 seconds.
>> You guys have made a lot of progress and
I look forward to all this. Thank you so
much.
>> Thank you, Paul. Uh, next we go to
Crystal.
Crystal, please unmute your line. You
have three minutes.
>> Greetings. My name is Crystal. I am the
owner of Lady Cana Apothecary. I have
been involved in the underground
cannabis and psilocybin community since
2017. I am elated for legaliz legalized
access to indigenous sacred medicine. My
priority when it comes to accessible
medic medication is not only removing
barriers to these sacred medicines, but
I believe it's important to uplift New
Mexicans and put a cap on migrating
practitioners, cultivators, and
facilitators. I believe we need to be
conscious of uplifting New Mexicans by
creating accessible programs and
education so our people may thrive.
Those of us in this space felt a direct
impact when medical cannabis was
legalized and the program allowed for
big corporations and outside sources to
infiltrate. I also believe it is
important to advocate for language to be
amended in the current law that allows
people to grow psilocybin but to not but
not to harvest it. Thank you for
considering our input. It's appreciated.
>> Thank you, Crystal.
Um,
okay. Next, it looks like we have um
Paul, but I feel like Paul just Okay, it
looks like he Nope. Um,
okay. Uh, Paul. Okay. Nope. Sorry.
Um,
okay. It looks like folks have lowered
their hands. Um,
if you wish to provide a public comment,
please raise your hand.
Thank you, Paul, for clarifying.
Okay, there are no additional hands
raised at this time. Oh, one just came
in. Um, Marina Robbins.
Um, please unmute your line. You have
three minutes.
>> Hi, everyone. Uh, my name is Marina
Robbins. I'm a doctor public health
candidate at UC Berkeley. I'm Navajo
from Wind Rock, Arizona and also grew up
in uh, Albuquerque, Santa Fe, New
Mexico. Um, I as a previous member on
the Colorado Natural Medicine Health Act
federally recognized American tribes and
indigenous communities working group um,
offering and I'm here offering a comment
in my capacity as a former member of
that group. Um, and I would share that
the report is out there. I would
encourage the board to look at the
Colorado Tribal Working Group report. Um
there's a lot of great information in
there around how we designed it to
address exploitation, uh
misappropriation,
uh cultural appropriation, biopiracy,
bioprospecting, engaging with, uh
grassroots indigenous organizations that
existed in co that exist in Colorado who
are doing conservation work, um uh local
native health organizations, uh urban
native health organizations, and I
understand that New Mexico has a uh 23
federally recognized tribes um who have
all their own languages, government
systems. Um, and so I'm encouraging this
board and the the committee that's going
to be formed to address uh indigenous
communities to engage with tribes early
to be transparent, consistent um to uh
be accountable to the actions and to the
plans that are put into place um with
tribes um at the in leadership and what
would it look like for tribes to come
together and learn about and respond to
the medical psilocybin act. Um and
whether they're for it, they have the
infrastructure to implement it. They're
against it. It's not their medicine.
It's not their way or um they need more
education, more information. How is this
going to affect them at the community
level, at the healthcare level, at the
tribal administrative um legal level?
So, just putting that out there. I know
it's huge. I know it's big, but um I
think New Mexico is uh in a good
position. It's an opportunity for New
Mexico to move forward with tribal
engagement in an ethical uh way. So,
thank you all for being here and I I
support everyone's work here.
>> Thank you.
Uh next we'll go to um Senator Martin
Hickeyi. Please unmute your line.
Dominic, did you want to do an
introduction of the senator?
>> Oh, uh, I just wanted to welcome Senator
Hickeyi and thank you so much for
joining today. Um, so please, uh, go on
ahead with what whatever you would like
to say. Thank you for joining.
>> Uh,
thank you, Dominic, uh, Chris, Ian,
those are the names I can see. Uh,
Larry, uh, all the others for being
willing to sit on this board. It's
really critical. I was really glad to
see that you went through the bylaws
this morning having uh had boards and
served on boards. Uh it's a very
important function to know and
understand those as a board member. So
uh thank you for doing that. But mostly
thank you for just undertaking this
activity. I've
traveling for medical conferences and
meetings and honest to God people are
saying, "Wow, what's happening in New
Mexico around this? It sounds great."
And I think literally many other states
and I've been with other state
legislators recently are looking forward
to what you all come up with uh because
they think it is so necessary in their
state. So thank you for leading the way
and doing this and I wish everyone a
wonderful holiday. Thank you.
>> Happy holidays, Senator.
>> Thank you, Senator.
Okay, next we'll go to uh Timothy Scott.
Please unmute your line. You have three
minutes.
>> Um, yes. Can everybody hear me? Okay.
>> Yes.
>> Yes. Uh, well, first off, you know, I
just moved to New Mexico probably two
years ago, and I come from a state where
this type of practice isn't even thought
of. So, I just wanted to say that I
appreciate the senator and the board and
everybody involved in maybe getting
something going as far as this research.
And I think that's all I got. Thank you
guys.
>> Thank you.
>> If you wish to provide uh public
comment, please raise your hand.
Okay. Uh, at this time since we do not
see any additional hands raised, um,
we'll conclude the public comment. Just
as a note, as I've been putting up on
the slides on screen, if you are
interested in providing public comment
but did not wish to speak during the
meeting, you can send written public
comment to the program email at
medical.silocybin
to.nm.gov.
and we will include it in the meeting
record. In order to do so, please send
the comment by Monday, December 15th at
5:00 p.m. Thank you everyone. And uh
Ian, I just wanted to note that in
addition to Senator Hickey, Senator
Steinborn has also been in the meeting.
Um I'm not sure if he would like to
speak as well. Um Senator, if you would
like to speak, go ahead and uh raise
your hand if you don't mind.
Okay, Kathy, if you could unmute Senator
Steinborn.
>> Yep. Senator Steinborn, please uh please
unmute your line.
>> Okay, now I'm unmuted. Yeah.
>> Yeah, we can hear you.
>> All right. Yeah. Asking a politician to
speak, we'll we'll get a uh we'll get a
guaranteed response. Um good morning
everybody. good work today. It's just
great to see it along with Senator
Hickeyi. Senator Hickeyi was also just a
primary co-sponsor of the legislation
and a crucial guy. He's also a medical
doctor. He also ran health plans. I
mean, he's one of our leaders in the New
Mexico legislature really. And he was
the author of a bill that created the
first bill in the country to eliminate
co-pays from behavioral health doctor's
visits and medicine. And so when you do
those things and they don't cost you
anything, that was because of a law that
he passed. So he's I just just can't say
enough about him and he's he's he's very
strongly supportive of what we're doing
here. So um yeah, good work. This is
going to be a lot of work. We know and
uh get our arms around all the data and
the science and best practices and I
and I just wish you well because there's
a lot to do and a lot of details and
we're all in it together. So, um, thank
you all for your work as well.
Appreciate it and just look forward to
supporting your efforts. Thank you so
much.
>> Thank you, Senator.
>> Thank you, Senator. And Ian, we do not
have any additional uh individuals with
their hands raised. So, back to you for
conclusion of the meeting.
>> All righty. Well, if there is no further
business, I'll entertain a motion to
adjurnn.
I make a motion to adjourn.
>> Second.
>> Make a motion to adjurnn.
>> Perfect. And with those uh motion and no
objection, we adjourned at 11:11 a.m. on
12:12.
Kind of cute.
>> That is very cool. Thank you. This is
wonderful. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you everybody.